Guide to the James T. Sears Papers, 1918-2011 and undated, bulk 1950-2004 RL.01162
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Audiovisual Material, 1958-2004 and undated, 40 boxes
  - Videocassette Recordings, 1972-1985 and undated
    - Various Video Recordings
      - Undated, Sin or Murder? Who Created AIDS - Scolletta/Redman [TRT 62:00] (Box 38)
      - Undated, Stan Boyle (?) newscast (Box 38)
      - Undated, Wendy, Kate, and Carol interviewing Rose, Audrey and Danielle (Box 38)
    - Master copies for reel-to-reel recordings (OR1-OR12)
      - [CD-R. Closed to research use. Staff can use to make listening copies for research access.] (Box 39)
    - Other Media
      [RESTRICTIONS: Originals are CLOSED to use. Staff must arrange for use copies to be made for research access. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.]
      - David Diamond (openly gay composer, 1914-2005), interview by Carlos Dews and Dan Griffin, 2000 July 8, 2 CD-Rs (Box 40)
      - Helical scan video, unknown content, undated (Box 40)
      - unspecified (Box 40)
- Other Activities, 1991-2008 and undated, 2 boxes
  - Scholarlink Subseries, 1991-2004 and undated (2003-2004) (Box 41)
    An online referral service founded by Sears, linking academics with the business community and other sectors. Materials include correspondence, focus group sessions, feedback, several versions of proposals and business plans, Powerpoint presentation, and other various printed materials. Electronic material has been separated and mounted to the library server; for access to this material, please consult with a reference archivist.
  - Seabrook Island Community Subseries, 2006-2008 (Box 42)
    Drafts and research materials written and gathered by Sears, a resident of Seabrook Island (S.C.), for real estate columns in local newspapers: The Seabrooker, The Island Connection, The Island Eye News, and Ocean Tides. Issues addressed by Sears in these writings include the environment, land use, property zoning, and community organizing. Original complete issues of newspapers have been removed to Oversize Material.
- Personal Files, 1973-2008 and undated, 4 boxes
  Houses biographical information on James T. Sears, early education materials, early writings, newspaper clippings, and an essay written in 2007 in which Sears reflects on his career and the field of curriculum studies. Arranged in chronological order within subseries.
  [NOTE: Portions of this series are closed to use until five years after the donor's death.]
  - Biographical Subseries, 1974-2008 and undated
    - 1974-1983, Letters of recommendation (Box 43)
    - 1991-1993 and undated, Newspaper clippings (Box 43)
    - 1999-2002, Curriculum vitae (Box 43)
    - 2006, Grawemeyer Award (Box 43)
    - Fall 2007, Sears essay reminiscing about his career and the field of curriculum studies, published in American Educational Research Association Curriculum Studies Newsletter (Box 43)
    - 2008, Curriculum vita (Box 43)
  - Education Subseries, 1970-1990 and undated
    - 1970-1980, Class notes, 7 folders (Box 43)
    - 1973-1980, Sociology, classroom notes (Box 43)
    - 1975-1981, High school and college writings, 2 folders (Box 44)
    - unspecified (Box 44)
    - 1976, Ronald Reagan paper, 2 folders (Box 44)
    - 1980, Analysis, strategies, proposals (Box 44)
    - 1990, Prisms (Box 44)
    - Undated, Law (Box 44)
  - Personal Files (CLOSED) (Box 45-46)
    [Closed to use until five years after the donor's death.]
- Photographs, 1918-1989 and undated, bulk 1980s-1990s, 4 boxes
  Chiefly black-and-white photographic images used in Jim Sears' publications on gay history, as well as a few publicity shots of Sears, and casual snapshots of Sears at lectures, conferences, and book tours. Most of the research material was used to illustrate Rebels, Rubyfruit and Rhinestones and Lonely Hunters. Files of materials considered for use in a publication are identified with the original titles consisting of names of individuals, groups, or locales; contents can include photographs, paper printouts of images, other research material, clippings, permissions forms, and correspondence.
  Key communities represented in the research materials include Atlanta and New Orleans, though there are files on most Southern states. The various materials in the series cover the period from the late nineteenth century through the 1990s, with the bulk focusing on the 20th century. While the majority of images relate to urban issues, images of rural gay culture are also included; files on the Short Mountain Sanctuary and people associated with it (among them Milo [Guthrie] Pyne and Merril Mushroom) are notable in this regard.
  This series also includes a set of 21 signed 8x10 inch black-and-white portraits of gay activists, writers, and artists by noted photographer Robert Giardi. Giardi's subjects in alphabetical order: Paula Gunn Allen, Gloria Anzaldua, Perry Brass, Forman Brown (pseudonym Richard Meeker), Allen Ginsburg, Essex Hemphill, Dolores Kaich, Joan Larkin, Audre Lorde, Joan Nestle, Manuel Ramos Otero, Pat Parker, Felice Picano-Amagansett, Venita Porter, John Preston, James Purdy, Assotto Saint, Barbara Smith, Kitty Tsui, Carolyn Weather, and Jenny Wrenn; there is also a group portrait of the managing editors of RFD (publication of the Radical Faeries) at Short Mountain Sanctuary, an intentional gay community in rural Tennessee. The series is arranged alphabetically.
  Other photographs and images can also be found throughout the James Sears Papers; additionally, hundreds of digital images related to this series and to other materials in the collection have been separated and mounted on a library server; please contact Research Services for access to these images.
  - AIDS (Box 47)
  - Alabama (Box 47)
  - ALFA (Box 47)
  - ALFA/Atlanta (Box 47)
  - Atlanta (Box 47)
  - Blue (Box 47)
  - Bourbon (Box 47)
  - Bragg [Laura], 8 folders (Box 47)
  - Carter, Logan (Box 47)
  - Catalogue photos sent (Box 47)
  - Chronicle newspaper for Hall [Gordon], 3 folders (Box 47)
  - Clearwater, Marge, 2 folders (Box 47)
  - Copies of photo release forms (Box 47)
  - Crew [Louis] (Box 47)
  - Day [Greg] picture (Box 47)
  - Drag, 3 folders (Box 47)
  - Duke (Box 47)
  - Early 20th century women/Vita, 3 folders (Box 47)
  - Faye, Frances, 2 folders (Box 47)
  - Feminist photos, 1920 (Box 47)
  - Gallery (Box 47)
  - Generations (Box 47)
  - Giardi, Robert photographs, 1986-1989 (Box 48)
  - Hall [Gordon Langley], 3 folders (Box 47)
  - Inman, [Richard] (Box 47)
  - Jackson, Tony (Box 47)
  - Johns Committee, 2 folders (Box 47)
  - Jones, Elliott (Box 47)
  - Kepner, [Jim] (Box 47)
  - Lambe, Ron (Box 47)
  - [Clarke,] Lige (Box 49)
  - Martin, Marcelina (Box 49)
  - March on Washington (Box 49)
  - Minstrel shows (Box 49)
  - Matlovich, [Leonard], 2 folders (Box 49)
  - M[onteagudo], Jesse (Box 49)
  - Mushroom, Merril, 3 folders (Box 49)
  - New Orleans, 2 folders (Box 49)
  - Newspaper headers, 1950s-1960s harassment, 2 folders (Box 49)
  - Nichols, Jack, 3 folders (Box 49)
  - North Carolina (Box 49)
  - P, Miss, 2 folders (Box 49)
  - [Penelope,] Julia (Box 49)
  - Pioneer photos (Box 49)
  - Pre-1998 (Box 49)
  - Pyne, Milo, 4 folders (Box 49)
  - RFD photos (misc) (Box 49)
  - Running Water/Lambe, Ron (Box 49)
  - Sears, James, 5 folders (Box 49)
  - Shaw, Clay (Box 49)
  - Short Mountain (Box 49)
  - Simpson chapter (Box 50)
  - Sinister Wisdom/Feminary (Box 50)
  - South Carolina (Box 50)
  - Southeast conference (Box 50)
  - Tennessee (Box 50)
  - Texas, 2 folders (Box 50)
  - Turner, Herman David (Box 50)
  - Unidentified, 2 folders (Box 50)
  - University at North Carolina at Chapel Hill photo archive (Box 50)
  - [Wanstrom,] Rita, 2 folders (Box 50)
  - Wilson, Pete/Cubbs, Elizabeth (Box 50)
  - Zamora, Pedro (Box 50)
- Professional Papers, 1984-2007 and undated, 26 boxes
  Research materials, correspondence, publicity, drafts and proofs, administrative and editorial files, and other items documenting James T. Sears' career as an educator and author. Arranged into subseries in the following categories: conferences and organizations; professional correspondence; engagements and publicity; publishing files; and teaching, the largest file group. Further descriptions of each subseries follow. For personal correspondence and other files, consult the Personal Files Series.
  - Conferences and Organizations Subseries, 1985-2005, 2 boxes
    Chiefly composed of files relating to conferences Sears attended or coordinated, and organizations in which he played an active role. There are references to other conferences, mostly on teaching and curriculum studies, that appear in the Research and Writings Series as part of the subseries for certain publications; in addition, there may be some conference-related materials in the Engagements and Publicity Subseries of this series. Prominently represented organizations and conferences include: American Educational Research Association (AERA); the AERA Lesbian and Gay Studies Special Interest Group (SIG); and Curriculum and Pedagogy. Arranged in alphabetical order by name of conference or organization.
    - AERA -- Curriculum and Pedagogy, 14 folders (Box 51)
    - Curriculum and Pedagogy -- South Carolina Gay and Lesbian Pride (SC Pride), 12 folders (Box 52)
  - Professional Correspondence Subseries, 1994-2007, 2 boxes
    Exchanges between Sears and other authors and colleagues found separately from other materials in the collection. Large amounts of professional correspondence can be found throughout the writings and other publications files and in the records relating to Sears' academic positions.
    - 1994-2005, 37 folders (Box 53)
    - 2005-2007, 14 folders (Box 54)
  - Engagements and Publicity Subseries, 1991-2007 and undated, 5 boxes
    Files document the many speaking engagements and publicity related to Sears' publications, as well as other non-academic activities. There is a mix of folders with distinct names and folders that group materials by year, but in general the two categories are comprised as follows: engagements materials derive from events such as speeches, interviews, and readings, and include the texts of speeches, correspondence, clippings, brochures, other printed materials, and photographs; publicity materials contain correspondence, clippings, and printed material such as brochures and flyers regarding Sears' book-length works, primarily Lonely Hunters and Rebels, Rhinestones, and Rubyfruit. A number of reviews of Sears' work, primarily in the gay press, are also included. Correspondence in this series pertains to efforts by Sears and his publicists to secure speaking or reading engagements at bookstores and other venues in 1997 and 2001. Although a few items relating to Sears' published work on curriculum are included, his conference papers on that topic are located in the Conferences and Organizations Subseries above and his academic lectures in the Teaching Subseries below. Arranged in chronological order.
    - 1991-1994, 24 folders (Box 55)
    - 1994-1998, 16 folders (Box 56)
    - 1997-2001, 40 folders (Box 57)
    - 2001-2007, 23 folders (Box 58)
    - 2007 and undated, 10 folders (Box 59)
    - Publicity photographs, 1987-1991 and undated, 48 items (Box 59)
  - Publishing Files Subseries, 1997-2007, 1 box
    Small group of files containing royalty statements, contracts for Sears' writings, contracts and other materials for submissions to works or series edited by Sears, publishers' correspondence, and other documents related to the publishing process. Files in the Research and Writings Series hold other similar documentation, including correspondence with publishers and copies of contracts. Arranged in original order as received.
    - 1997-2007, 7 folders (Box 59)
  - Teaching Subseries, 1984-2007 and undated, 17 boxes
    Arranged in the following groups: Brackenridge Internship in Teaching; Consulting; Department Files; and Closed Academic Files, which are closed to research until five years after the donor's death.
    - Brackenridge Internship in Teaching (BIT), 1984-1993 and undated
      Files of correspondence, interviews, and other papers that document Sears' involvement with the Bridenthal Internship in Teaching program, now known as the Brackenridge (BIT). A six-year study on teacher recruitment based on the BIT program culminated in a publication edited by Sears and several others, When Best Doesn't Equal Good: Educational Reform and Teacher Recruitment. A Longitudinal Study (1994). Other materials on BIT are located in the Research and Writings Series, Other Publications Subseries, under that title. Arranged in order as received, roughly chronological.
      - Correspondence, 1984-1986 and undated, 1 folder (Box 60)
      - Course Materials for BIT, 1984-1993
        - 1984-1990 (Box 60)
        - 1985-1993 (Box 61)
        - 1984-1993 (Box 62)
      - Interviews, 1984-1992
        - General files, 30 folders (Box 62)
        - General files, 3 folders (Box 63)
        - Individuals, 16 folders (Box 63)
        - Individuals, 9 folders (Box 64)
      - Journals and Papers, 1985-1992, 16 folders (Box 64)
    - Consulting Work, 1988-2003
      [Boxes 65-66 are CLOSED to research for 25 years from latest date.]
      Materials gathered here derive from work Sears has done for various universities and organizations on issues related to gays and lesbians on campus. Most of these documents originated from Penn State University, and includes documentation on a proposed Center for Sexualities and the Professions in its School of Education. Files include correspondence, reports of task forces and committees at various universities, and a variety of printed material. Arranged in alphabetical order by folder title.
      - EDLP 832--Penn State Forensic Study, 24 folders (Box 65)
      - Penn State Outreach--University of South Carolina Campus Climate Survey, 15 folders (Box 66)
    - Course Materials, 1985-2004 and undated
      Large group of files containing documentation on courses taught by Sears chiefly at the University of South Carolina and Penn State. Course topics include sexual identity, teaching and the creation of "sex ed" curricula, and political movements. Files include correspondence, syllabi, notes, lectures, comments and evaluations by students, proposals for courses or programs, and other files. One group of folders deals with a controversial course taught on the Religious Right. Also contains materials relating to Sears' teaching activities as a faculty member at the University of South Carolina and College of Charleston. Arranged in order received, roughly chronological.
      - Courses, 1985-2004 and undated (Box 67-75)
    - Committee Work, 1991-2004 and undated
      Mainly correspondence and documents gathered by Sears through his participation at the University of South Carolina on various academic committees and working groups. Arranged in order as received.
      - Files, 1991-2004 and undated, 12 folders (Box 75)
    - Closed Academic Files, 1999-2007 and undated
      Scope and Contents
      Correspondence and other documents derived from Sear's work with various tenure committees and working groups. Arranged in order as received.
      [Box 76 CLOSED to research for 25 years from latest date.]
      - Academic files (Box 76)
- Research and Writings, 1941-2007 and undated, bulk 1975-2005, 176 boxes
  This largest series in the collection houses research materials, correspondence, publicity, drafts and proofs, administrative and editorial files, and other materials documenting James T. Sears' career as researcher, author, and editor. Organized into four subseries: Major Works, Other Publications, Research Files, and Writings by Others.
  The largest subseries, Major Works, features files of correspondence, drafts and proofs, research materials, and other items related to the following major book-length works by Sears (presented in chronological order) on the history of homosexuality and gay identity in the South, and the history of the gay rights movement: Growing Up Gay in the South: Race, Gender, and Journeys of the Spirit (1990); Lonely Hunters: an Oral History of Lesbian and Gay Southern Life, 1948-1968 (1997); Rebels, Rhinestones, and Rubyfruit: Queering Space in the Stonewall South (2001); Behind the Mask of the Mattachine: the Hal Call Chronicles and the Early Movement for Homosexual Emancipation (2006); and John and Edwin (2009), a volume on early gay history seen through the lens of a relationship between two men from the South. Lonely Hunters, Rebels, Rhinestones, and Rubyfruit, and Behind the Mask of the Mattachine were published as volumes in a series on gay history; another volume on homosexuality in the U.S. before 1950 was planned but is currently unpublished. Detailed descriptions follow below; titles are organized chronologically by date of publication.
  The Other Publications Subseries chiefly consists of the following types of materials: files relating to essays and chapters contributed by Sears to book-length works; files deriving from his editorial work for books and journals, including the gay studies journal Empathy; and conference papers written by Sears, some of which may be unpublished. A number of the writings in this subseries relate to Sears' pioneering work on the development of a classroom curriculum for teaching sexuality and gender identity. In addition, this series houses files of book reviews written by Sears. Reviews of his own publications can be found in the Major Works Subseries, or in the Publicity Series. Subseries is arranged in alphabetical order by title.
  The Research Files Subseries contains extensive files maintained by Sears on various topics relevant to his written work, including gay culture in the Southern U.S. (especially Florida, North Carolina, and Alabama), gays in the military, and sexuality in the Philippines; some material was unpublished while other material was utilized in published works. Arranged in alphabetical order by subject.
  The smallest and final subseries, Writings by Others, houses writings by other individuals which were either sent to Sears for review, or used by Sears in his research. These are arranged alphabetically by author last name.
  Many of the writings and other related materials in this collection were received as electronic files. The contents of each disk have been migrated to a library server. Please consult a reference archivist for access to these and other electronic files.
  - Major Works Subseries, 1941-2007 and undated, 104 boxes
    Correspondence, research, contributor, and administrative files pertaining to major book-length works by Sears. Arranged chronologically by publication date; within, alphabetically or in original order as received.
    - Growing up Gay in the South: Race, Gender, and Journeys of the Spirit (1990), 1975-1992 and undated, 6 boxes
      Files organized into sections of correspondence, drafts and proofs, interviews, and research files. Correspondence is arranged alphabetically; drafts and proofs in order received. Interviews comprise three boxes: the first two contain complete interviews and interview notes, and are arranged by first name and case number as assigned by Sears. Research files include a set of folders (mostly but not all contiguous and marked "QSL") housing materials related to Sears' paper, Attitudes, Experiences, and Feelings of Guidance Counselors in Working with Homosexual Students: A Report on the Quality of School Life for Southern Gay and Lesbian Students (1988), which formed the basis for the book. The early research for this paper was in part supported by the Gay and Lesbian Advocacy Research Project (GLARP), whose name appears on many folders. The third box contains what seem to be aggregates of these interviews, and are arranged according to case number. Audio recordings on cassette are also available for many interviews; these are housed in the Audiovisual Series.
      - Correspondence, 1987-1990
        - 8 folders (Box 77)
      - Drafts and Proofs, 1988 and undated
        - 6 folders (Box 77)
      - Interviews, 1986-1988
        - Full transcripts (Box 78-79)
        - Aggregate interviews (Box 80)
      - Publicity, 1987-1992 and undated
        - 5 folders (Box 81)
      - Research Files, 1985-1988 and undated
        - American Educational Research Association paper, 1988 (Box 81-82)
        - Book references, undated (Box 81-82)
        - Chapter 13 (?), undated (Box 81-82)
        - Coping Behaviors (American Educational Research Association), 1988 (Box 81-82)
        - Counselor surveys, undated (Box 81-82)
        - Curriculum Theory conference paper, 1987 (Box 81-82)
        - Debutante Ball, Raleigh, North Carolina; clippings, 1975 and 1987-1988 (Box 81-82)
        - Developing a Sense of Difference, 1987 (Box 81-82)
        - Draft: Feelings and Attitudes of Educators Toward Homosexuality and Homosexual Students, undated (Box 81-82)
        - Gay book appendices: research instruments (?), undated (Box 81-82)
        - Growing up Gay in the South appendix, 1985 (Box 81-82)
        - Miscellaneous references and chapter quotes (?), undated (Box 81-82)
        - Notes, undated (Box 81-82)
        - Originals, educators' questions, undated (Box 81-82)
        - Pre-service teachers' knowledge, attitudes about homosexuality, undated (Box 81-82)
        - Professional interview questions, undated (Box 81-82)
        - Quality of School Life for Gay and Lesbian Adolescents proposals and papers, 1986-1989 and undated, 10 folders (Box 81-82)
        - References for gay quality of school life paper, undated (Box 81-82)
        - Thomas from the rebels, undated (Box 81-82)
        - South Carolina guidance counselor questions, 1987 (Box 81-82)
        - South Carolina history, undated (Box 81-82)
        - Summary of 36 rebel cases, undated (Box 81-82)
        - Organization of the original 36 rebels, undated (Box 81-82)
    - Lonely Hunters: an Oral History of Lesbian and Gay Southern Life, 1948-1968 (1997), 1954-1998 and undated, 10 boxes
      Also referred to in earlier material as "Generations," this volume was published as the first in a series on history of homosexuality and gay movements in the U.S. Contains groups of drafts and proofs, publicity, and research files. Drafts and proofs are arranged in the order in which they were received. Several files of proofs or drafts include the 1995 prospectus, correspondence with Sears' colleagues and proofreaders, including Kepner's foreword, an interview with Barbara Gittings (Daughters of Bilitis founder) for the afterword, Gordon Hall (Dawn Langley Simmons), and Jack Nichols. Publicity files are arranged alphabetically, and include book reviews, awards, book tour schedules, promotional statements, and a video. Research files, arranged alphabetically, include chapter and interview notes, early research materials about gender, early homosexuality cases, and gay identity, as well as correspondence and research materials relating to book subjects Jack Nichols, Dawn Langley Simmons, and Sue Sponnoble. The last three boxes of research files pertain to an inquiry into homosexuality at the University of Florida in the late fifties; they contain depositions, statements, and court documents pertaining to the Johns Committee proceedings; these documents are arranged in order as received.
      - Correspondence, 1995-1997
        - 2 folders (Box 83)
      - Drafts and Proofs, 1995-1997
        - 25 folders (Box 83-86)
      - Publicity, 1997-1998
        - 24 folders (Box 86-87)
      - Research Files, 1954-1996 and undated
        - Braggman's interview notes, 1994 (Box 87A)
        - Civil Rights chapter, 1996 (Box 87A)
        - Ed Wall scandal: clippings, 1956 (Box 87A)